A Guide to the Records of the Policy Office: Conferences and Special Projects of Governor Lawrence Douglas Wilder, 1983-1992
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records of the Policy Office: Conferences and Special Projects of Governor Lawrence Douglas Wilder, 1983-1992
The Library of Virginia
34265
8.35 cu. ft. (23 boxes)
Virginia. Governor (1990-1994: Wilder)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred from Governor Lawrence Douglas Wilder on 31 October 1996.
Biographical Information
Lawrence Douglas Wilder was born in Richmond, Va., on January 17, 1931. He graduated from Virginia Union University in 1951 and afterwards was drafted into the Army, where he served in the Korean War from 1952-1953 and received a bronze star. He then attended the Howard University School of Law and graduated in 1959. Douglas Wilder was elected to the Virginia Senate in 1969 as the first African American member since Reconstruction and served in the Senate for five terms. In 1985, he was elected to the office of Lieutenant Governor as the first African American to be elected to statewide office in Virginia. L. Douglas Wilder won the election for Governor of Virginia in 1989 and served from January 13, 1990 to January 14, 1994. He was the first African American to be elected as Governor in United States.
During the Wilder Administration, the Policy Office was headed by Walter McFarlane, Executive Assistant for Policy, and four Special Assistants: Richard Taylor (Health and Human Resources, and Education), Robert Blue (Finance and Natural Resources), Jeff Nuechterlein (Economic Development and Transportation), and Lynne Porfiri (Administration and Public Safety). The Policy Office was responsible for review and coordination of all policy matters, including: review of proposed legislation from agencies and Cabinet; formulation of the Governor's legislative initiatives; tracking legislation and serving as legislative liaison; review of General Assembly approved legislation submitted to the Governor for signature, amendment or veto; review of death penalty clemency requests, as well as other pardon and restoration of rights requests; review of legal settlements and other legal matters from the Office of the Attorney General's Office; review of proposed regulations; review of all matters pertaining to the judiciary and writs of habeas corpus; review of proposed executive orders; assistance with speech writing; serving as staff for Governor's special commissions; administrative support for Governor's Fellows program; serving as special interest liaison; acting as in-house counsel; and all correspondence with policy implications or pertaining to sensitive or controversial issues requiring legal overview.
Scope and Content
Records of the Policy Office: Conferences and Special Projects of Governor Lawrence Douglas Wilder, 1983-1992, are housed in 23 boxes and are arranged chronologically by date of conference or special project. Includes agendas, brochures, calendars, clippings, correspondence, information packets, invitations, license plates, lists, logos, maps, memorandums, menus, minutes, notes, photographs, proceedings, schedules, and other documents detailing conferences and special projects during the administration of Governor Wilder, along with the previous administrations of Governor Robb and Governor Baliles. Conferences and Special Projects cover drugs, education, foreign trade, health care, physical fitness, rural development, state involvement in Desert Shield/Desert Storm, commissioning of the USS George Washington, as well as other topics.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged chronologically by date of conference or special project.
Contents List
- Reevaluation of State Government, 1983-1984.
  - Program development, 1982-1983. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Conference, 31 March-1 April 1983. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Conference papers, 13 May 1983. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Invitation list for conference, 13 May 1983. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Remarks by participants, 13 May 1983. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Collegial bodies meeting, 14 June 1983. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Conference invitees/attendees, 23-24 September 1983. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Conference proceedings, 23-24 September 1983. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence (following), 23-24 September 1983. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Fundraising, 23-24 September 1983. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Operation manual (folder 1 of 2), 23-24 September 1983. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Operation manual (folder 2 of 2), 23-24 September 1983. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Press, 23-24 September 1983. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Pre-registration packets, 23-24 September 1983. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Registration packet--at door, 23-24 September 1983. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Speakers' remarks, 23-24 September 1983. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Survey responses, 23-24 September 1983. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Thank you letters--drafts, 23-24 September 1983. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - The Governor's Report on Critical Reevaluation: An Assessment of the Secretrial System and the Proposed Realignments of the Executive Branch, 24 January 1984. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Governor's Report on the Feasibility of Further Realignments in Executive Branch Agencies, 31 December 1984. (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Summit of Industrialized Nations (Williamsburg), 28-30 May 1983.
  - Clippings. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Letterhead. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - License plate. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Media handbook. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Planning and operation--College of William and Mary. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Planning and operation--state agencies: Industrial Development, Jamestown-Yorktown Foundation, DMV, ABC, and Taxation. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Planning and operation--state agencies: State Police, DGS, State Highways and Transportation. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Planning and operation--state agencies: Budget and Planning, various agencies. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Summit packet (meeting). (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Summit packet (Colonial Williamsburg). (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Treaty of Paris Bicentennial (Paris, France), 29 August-10 September 1983.
  - Papers. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Schedule and arrangements. (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Southern Governors' Association 50th Anniversary meeting (Williamsburg), 8-11 July 1984.
  - Briefing materials for governors. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Brochure. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Finances. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Finances--contracts. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Information packets. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Information packet--1980 SGA meeting in Williamsburg. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - License plate. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Planning. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Operations manuals (folder 1 of 3). (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Operations manuals (folder 2 of 3). (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Operations manuals (folder 3 of 3). (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Thank you letters--patrons. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Thank you letters--state. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Thank you letters--others. (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Olympics ceremony (Richmond), 17 September 1984.
  - A Salute to Virginia's Olympic Participants. (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Blue Ridge Parkway 50th Anniversary, 9-14 September 1985.
  - The Blue Ridge Parkway Milepost, Fall-Winter, 1984-1985. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Blue Ridge Parkway information packet. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Clippings. (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - 50th anniversary celebration committee correspondence and papers. (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - 50th anniversary celebration committee meeting. (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - 50th anniversary celebration committee packet. (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Motion Picture Development committee. (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Southern Living, Setember 1985. (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Southeast U.S./Japan Conference (The Homestead, Hot Springs), 12-14 October 1986.
  - Buses. (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Contracts. (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Coordinators correspondence/information. (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence. (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Delegation information packet and extra material (including delegation badges). (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Delegate information packet (South Carolina delegate). (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Delegate information packet (Virginia delegate). (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Delegate listing. (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Delegation--Virginia. (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Facility diagrams. (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Fast Track books on Tape--How to Do Business with the Japanese. (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Financial records. (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Fireworks. (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Food, including menus. (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Gifts. (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Governor's briefing package. (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Homestead. (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Homestead--information packet. (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Information and schedule. (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - New Virginains (entertainment). (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Notes. (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Operations manual. (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Photographs. (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Preliminary site visits. (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Press--public relations. (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Proceedings. (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Signage--banner, flags. (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Speeches--proceedings. (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Spouse program. (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Thank you letters. (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Translation--Hargrove. (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - VHS tape, 13 October 1986. (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - VHS tape, 14 October 1986. (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Working schedules. (Box 9, Folder 2)
- Magna Carta, August 1987.
  - Mobile exhibition tour of Virginia. (Box 9, Folder 3)
- State Police--Conferences, 1988.
  - Planning. (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Portrait Unveiling--State Senator Edward E. Willey (Richmond), 11 February 1988.
  - Budget. (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Papers. (Box 9, Folder 6)
- Southern Growth Policies Board meeting (Richmond), 8-10 June 1988.
  - Briefing for governor/background information. (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Clippings. (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Finances. (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Information packet. (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Information packet. (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Operations manual. (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Papers. (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Proceedings. (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - State Police. (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Virginia Museum of Fine Arts information. (Box 10, Folder 3)
- Kickoff for Wine Month, September-October 1988.
  - Papers. (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Southeast United States/Korea Economic Council (Williamsburg), 12-15 November 1988.
  - Accommodations. (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Briefings for governor. (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Colonial Williamsburg--activities. (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Colonial Williamsburg--correspondence. (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Colonial Williamsburg--printed matter, floor plans. (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Finances. (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Madisonians (entertainment). (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Minutes, discussion notes, correspondence. (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous--press notes. (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Operations manual. (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Planning. (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Registration packet. (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Rhim correspondence. (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Thank you letters. (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Walk through, 13-14 May 1988. (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - William and Mary seminar--Korea. (Box 11, Folder 5)
- Soviet Visit with National Governors' Association (cancelled), 16-17 November 1988.
  - Correspondence and memorandums. (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Potential attendees. (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Schedules, activities. (Box 11, Folder 8)
- National Governors' Association--New Governors Seminar (Charlottesville), 17-19 November 1988.
  - Accommodations. (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Attendees. (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Bills processed (folder 1 of 2). (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Bills processed (folder 2 of 2). (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Boar's Head Inn. (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Finances--private account. (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Host committee. (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Host committee collection and thank yous. (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Hotel setup sheets. (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Layout--UVA: Old Cabell Hall. (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Layouts--UVA: Culbreath Theater, Rotunda, Carr's Hall-president's home. (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Maps--Charlottesville, UVA. (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Operations manual. (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Planning schedules--conference calls. (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Phones. (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Program. (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Registration packet--file sample. (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Seminar packet. (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Spouse actitivies/schedule. (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Staff responsibilies--contacts. (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - State Police. (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Thank you letters. (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Thursday night. (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Transportation. (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Walk through--May. (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Walk through--September. (Box 13, Folder 9)
- Presidential Visits.
  - University of Virginia Alumni News, January-February 1989. (Box 13, Folder 10)
- President's Education Summit (Charlottesville), 27-28 September 1989.
  - Accommodations and attendees. (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Briefing for governor. (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Calendar and schedules. (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Contacts. (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Convocation. (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - Finances. (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - Floor plans--UVA. (Box 13, Folder 17)
  - Gifts. (Box 13, Folder 18)
  - Information packets. (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Minutes. (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - News clippings and press releases. (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - News clippings--Cavalier Daily. (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - News clippings--University Journal. (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - News clippings--USA Today. (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Past summits. (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Photographs--Boar's Head Inn. (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Photographs--Cabell Hall and Lawn walk. (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Photographs--closing statements (general shots). (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Photographs--convocation. (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Photographs--president's breakfast (Rotunda). (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Photographs--press briefing. (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - Photographs--Rotunda session. (Box 14, Folder 14)
  - Photographs--staff dinner. (Box 14, Folder 15)
  - Pre-summit information. (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Security. (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Site visits. (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Spouse program. (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Staff dinner; president's dinnr. (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Staffing. (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Thank you letters. (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Transportation. (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - White House correspondence. (Box 15, Folder 9)
- Southern Regional Education Board Legislative Advisory Committee meeting (Williamsburg), 3-6 October 1989.
  - Finances. (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Fundraising. (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Groaning board. (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - Jamestown. (Box 15, Folder 13)
  - Ladies' lunch and program. (Box 15, Folder 14)
  - Thank you letters. (Box 15, Folder 15)
  - Virginia invitees. (Box 15, Folder 16)
  - William and Mary session and reception. (Box 15, Folder 17)
  - Work Conference papers. (Box 15, Folder 18)
- Yorktown Victory Center Renovation, 4 January 1990.
  - Groundbreaking. (Box 15, Folder 19)
- National Governors' Association New Governors Seminar--Governor Wilder (Williamsburg), 26-27 January 1990.
  - Hotel accommodations. (Box 15, Folder 20)
  - Office of State Services--retreat materials. (Box 15, Folder 21)
  - Papers. (Box 15, Folder 22)
  - Thank you correspondence. (Box 15, Folder 23)
- Drug Summit (Richmond), 16-17 April 1990.
  - Artwork, logo, floor plans, signs. (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Dinner invitees. (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Conference proceedings. (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Drug control strategy. (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Finances. (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Initial mailing to potential attendees. (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Mementos. (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - News clippings. (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Operations manual. (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Planning schedule. (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Press kit (folder 1 of 2). (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - Press kit (folder 2 of 2). (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - Pride Team. (Box 16, Folder 13)
  - Regional sessions. (Box 16, Folder 14)
  - Speeches. (Box 16, Folder 15)
  - Steering committee. (Box 16, Folder 16)
  - Tactical sessions. (Box 16, Folder 17)
  - Tactical/regional sessions--attendees. (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Thank you letters. (Box 17, Folder 2)
- Rural Development Conference (Roanoke), 20-21 September 1990.
  - Attendees. (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence. (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Conference brochures and packets. (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Finances. (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Media packets, handouts. (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous--stickers, gifts, etc. (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Operations manual (folder 1 of 2). (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Operations manual (folder 2 of 2). (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - Planning meetings/briefs. (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - Pre-conference mailings. (Box 17, Folder 12)
  - Program. (Box 17, Folder 13)
  - Reports. (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Rural Development Task Force. (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Strategy/regional/facilitators. (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Thank you letters. (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - VHS tape. (Box 18, Folder 5)
- Desert Shield/Desert Storm, Fall 1990-1991.
  - Ceremonies and Events (folder 1 of 2). (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Ceremonies and Events (folder 2 of 2). (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous. (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - News clippings. (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Personnel shortages. (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Proclamations and certificates of recognition. (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Threats and security. (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Veterans Administration and Federal medical/health. (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Veteran benefits. (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Virginians killed in action. (Box 19, Folder 8)
- President's Council on Physical Fitness Summit (Richmond), 12 September 1991.
  - Arnold Schwarzenegger visit. (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Arnold Schwarzenegger visit follow-up. (Box 19, Folder 10)
- Virginia Drug Summit (Charlottesville), 14-15 April 1992.
  - Attendees lists and session assignments. (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Conference proceedings. (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Evaluations and thank you letters. (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Financial. (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Governor's speech. (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Information packets. (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Logo,signs and tags, teaser. (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - Operations manual. (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - Planning schedule. (Box 20, Folder 9)
  - Press information. (Box 20, Folder 10)
  - Registration material. (Box 20, Folder 11)
  - Summit exhibitions. (Box 20, Folder 12)
  - Summit program. (Box 20, Folder 13)
- Great Virginia Workout (Richmond), 13 May 1992.
  - Papers. (Box 20, Folder 14)
  - Photographs and negatives. (Box 20, Folder 15)
  - Press materials. (Box 20, Folder 16)
  - Thank you letters. (Box 20, Folder 17)
- Health Care Summit (Chantilly), 7-9 June 1992.
  - Finances. (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Operations manual. (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Papers. (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Registration mailer and list. (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Signs and media. (Box 21, Folder 5)
- USS George Washington Commissioning (Norfolk), 4 July 1992.
  - Activities subcommittee meeting, 18 February 1992. (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Business/Metro ads. (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - Commemorative pin. (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - Committee activities vs. Navy. (Box 21, Folder 9)
  - Committee organization meeting, 13 December 1991. (Box 21, Folder 10)
  - Committee meeting, 22 January 1992. (Box 21, Folder 11)
  - Committee meeting, 27 March 1992. (Box 21, Folder 12)
  - Committee meeting, 8 May 1992. (Box 21, Folder 13)
  - Committee meeting, 10 June 1992. (Box 21, Folder 14)
  - Commissioning committee papers, 1990-1992. (Box 21, Folder 15)
  - Commissioning committee logo. (Box 21, Folder 16)
  - Congressional letter. (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence--general. (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - Crew names and origins--Virginians. (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Fundraising (folder 1 of 4). (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - Fundraising (folder 2 of 4). (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - Fundraising (folder 3 of 4). (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - Fundraising/finances (folder 4 of 4). (Box 22, Folder 7)
  - George Washington University event. (Box 22, Folder 8)
  - Legislative reception, 22 January 1992. (Box 22, Folder 9)
  - Mt. Vernon ceremony. (Box 22, Folder 10)
  - News clippings. (Box 22, Folder 11)
  - Officers--USS George Washington. (Box 22, Folder 12)
  - Picture of USS George Washington. (Box 22, Folder 13)
  - Previous commissionings. (Box 22, Folder 14)
  - Programs. (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - Resolution and recognition (General Assembly), 22 January 1992. (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - Ship's activities. (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - Virginia House (Norfolk Naval Station) event, 26 March 1992. (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - Stanley Walker Marriott reception, 2 July 1992. (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - George Washington quotes for plaques. (Box 23, Folder 6)
- Southern States and Central America Summit (Charlottesville), 28 July 1992.
  - Correspondence and media. (Box 23, Folder 7)
  - Finances. (Box 23, Folder 8)
  - Invitees. (Box 23, Folder 9)
  - Monticello. (Box 23, Folder 10)
  - Operations manual. (Box 23, Folder 11)
  - Planning schedule/contacts/logistics. (Box 23, Folder 12)
  - Registration information. (Box 23, Folder 13)
  - Spouse program. (Box 23, Folder 14)